hello traders in this video we will
cover a full course on Smart money
trading from a starter level to an
advanced level by the end of the video
you should be able to have enough
knowledge to slowly become profitable of
course with patience and practice so
without making the introduction longer
let's get started the first chapter is
Market structure the market has three
types of movements the uptrend the
uptrend is the price structure that
repeatedly breaks highs and maintains
the price above the last lows the
uptrend is confirmed once price first
goes up then retraces back breaks the
previous High while not breaking the
previous low and this process usually
repeats until a reversal pattern that
we're going to talk about soon so the
price again retraces doesn't break the
last low so the pullback ends above the
last low then price breaks the past high
and so on this was a representation on
how high time frame price action looks
like on an uptrend but usually the
market structure is not that easy
you will more often see Price look
somewhat like this so the uptrend starts
by a price movement to the upside than a
pullback notice how the price structure
looks different than the structure from
the last representation but the
direction is the same the reason is that
the pullback from the uptrend is
actually a low time frame downtrend that
turns into a reversal into an uptrend
basically the end of the pullback is
where both time frames so the high time
frame and low time frame align and move
in the same direction then the the
uptrend confirms after the time frames
align and price breaks the last high and
essentially the same type of high time
frame price action repeats until a
reversal the low time frame downtrend
and the high time frame uptrend so we
are talking about the pullback it will
likely look different since obviously
price reflects the buy and sell orders
that are executed so fast especially on
liquid markets like Forex and the stock
market but the direction is the same we
will shortly cover why price action
differs but has the same direction and
it's all related to liquidity the second
type of market movement is the
downtrend oppositely to the uptrend the
downtrend is a market structure movement
that repeatedly breaks the past lows
while holding the price below the last
high this movement is often
characterized by a lower low and lower
high so the high time frame trend is a
downtrend then the pullback on a
downtrend is to the upside meaning that
this pullback is a low time frame
uptrend that reverse and align with the
high time frame Trend once the pullback
ends and practically after it dumps down
and breaks the past
lows this is the simplest explanation
and representation of the downtrend now
let's learn how price action actually
looks like on a more complex example so
in a downtrend the price action starts
by a downside movement then a low time
frame uptrend on the pullback and then a
break of the
lows this structure repeats pull back to
the upside but the upside movement is
unable able to break highs then downside
movement and break of the lows the
downtrend is a market that favors short
sellers over buyers the third type of
market movement is the sideways Market
the sideways Market is represented by
Price action that is not trending and is
moving towards the same levels this type
of Market is often seen right before a
trend reversal for example you will
often see from an uptrend price stops
the uptrend characteristics of breaking
Highs but it also doesn't break the lows
this price action shows a psychology
change in Traders why does this move
happen for many reasons like buyers
closing their positions buyers not
opening more buying positions but also
short sellers aren't that active so it
leaves price moving towards the same
highs and lows for a short time period
these sideways Market structures usually
indicate a reversal so coming from an
uptrend into a sideways Market the price
breaks the lows of the sideways market
and turn into a downtrend the sideways
Market Market is very hard to properly
trade because the movement and Order
flow is so unclear there is a good
change you might get trapped in the
wrong direction and obviously unwanted
large losses in our trading account so
the key word The Secret of this sideways
Market is to wait for this boring
structure to break either side and look
for trading opportunities after strong
and weak levels a strong level is a
price level that price action has shown
that it is very hard to break and a weak
level is a price level level that price
action has shown that it is easy to
break so let's look at the simple
uptrend this is the low of the first
movement on uptrends we know that lows
are not broken so this is the first
strong level then price going up pulling
back and breaking the high so by
confirmation of the uptrend the lowest
point of the pullback is the next strong
low and the high that broke is the weak
high and this markup repeats
in the more complex example it is
slightly harder upside movement pullback
and break of the high here it is
important to know that these are the
strong lows and these are the weak highs
now in the downtrend knowing that a
downtrend has lows that break and highs
that maintain starting from the simple
price action price going down pull back
up then breaking the lows so the strong
levels are the levels that don't break
and they are these levels they are
strong highs and the weak levels are the
price levels that do break and they are
these so they are the weak lows on a
more complex price action the direction
is the same downside movement pull back
to the upside break of the lows the
strong Highs are the same and these are
the weak lows we will get into into
right now to explain in it more detail
internal and external levels the
external levels are structural price
levels in the high time frame the
internal levels are structural price
levels on the lower time frame let's
take the uptrend scenario first on the
simple structure it's easy the external
levels are the major highs and lows
there is no internal structure in this
example same goes for the simple
downtrend the only levels are the
external levels and they are each major
high and low now let's look into the
more complex price action upside pull
back and break to the upside first let's
identify the external levels they are
same as previous ones meaning each major
high and low now into the internal
levels the internal levels are as we
have said the low time frame structure
inside the high time frame so the
internal structure is the price action
of the pullback on the complex downtrend
now the downtrend is identified by an
impulsive downside movement a pullback
to the upside and a break of the lows
the external levels are the the major
highs and lows the internal structure is
the price action inside the pullback
and in a high time frame downtrend the
pullback is a low time frame uptrend and
these are the internal structures these
internal structures are very important
to identify trading opportunities we
will learn all important Concepts and
put them all together to analyze a chart
of fine trading setups the break of
structure the breakup structure is a
trading concept used by smart money used
to indicate a continuation of the main
Trend and a liquidation of the orders
that are against the trend starting from
a simple uptrend price going up pull
back and then breaks the high the level
that breaks the high is called a break
of structure and essentially it does the
same for the upcoming price action as
long as the market structure is still
bullish so basically as long as the
market is in an uptrend for Simplicity
reasons we can call them bullish breaks
of structure when price is in an uptrend
and on a simple downtrend price goes
down Pull backs to the upside and breaks
the lows the level that broke the lows
is the bearish break of structure and
the concept apply itself for the future
price action too as long as the market
structure follows the continuation of
the downtrend we will go into more
details on the complex price action
after we learn the next concept because
these two work together change of
character the change of character also
named as Market structure shift is
another concept used by smart money that
indicates the First Signal of a trend
reversal let's go straight into the
examples starting from a simple uptrend
price action price going up pull back
and breaks the high pull back breaks the
high pull back breaks the high knowing
that the uptrend is characterized by
higher highs and higher lows the change
of character begins once the next low
breaks the last low so essentially the
change of character signals a deviation
from the initial Trend this is where its
name comes from by Price changing how it
looks changing the order flow we can
also name the change of character as a
market structure shift they are
essentially the same concept concept but
it is important to know that the change
of character is only the First Signal of
a reversal it is not a confirmation
because what it can happen is price just
breaking the low and then going straight
to the upside essentially continuing the
uptrend this move is called a liquidity
sweep and we are going to talk about it
a bit later but now let's focus on the
actual valid change of character the
confirmation of a trend reversal comes
only when price goes up but is unable to
break the past high and then it goes
down by breaking lows so the price
action has printed on the chart the
market structure of a downtrend and more
often than not this validates a reversal
from an uptrend into a
downtrend now for the simple bearish
price action we know that the downtrend
structure prints the price going down
then pull back to the upside and break
of the lows pull back to the upside
break of the lows and it keeps
going the change of character in the
downtrend happens when the price doesn't
manage to break the last lows and it
breaks the last High indicating the
first signal that the market could
reverse from a downtrend into an uptrend
but be careful as the change of
character is not a confirmation the
confirmation of the trend reversal
happens when the price pulls back to the
downside doesn't manage to break the
last lows and it goes up breaking the
last high so essentially it invalidated
the downtrend fundamentals of lower lows
and lower highs and valid Val ated a
market structure shift to an uptrend by
creating higher lows and higher highs
now we will apply both the break of
structure and the change of character on
the same price action we will start from
the simple structure to the more complex
one which is closer to the action price
action and finally applying all the
knowledge to analyze on the charts so
starting from the simplest form of price
action on an uptrend price going up pull
back to the downside which is the higher
low break of the high that marks the
higher high and we apply the bullish
break of structure pull back to the
downside which is a higher low break of
the high being a higher high and keeps
going until the price breaks the past
low it breaks the higher low which
creates a lower high and this level is
the change of character or the market
structure shift then price goes up but
is unable to break the previous higher
high and it creates a lower high then it
breaks the previous lows which are the
lower lows and this level becomes the
bearish break of structure so this is
important confirmation that the market
has shifted from an uptrend into a
downtrend so the most likely scenario is
that the market will continue the
recently created downtrend by Price
pulling back to the upside not managing
to break the last highs and it becomes a
lower high and soon after break of the
lows so another bearish break of
structure and price action constantly
repeats until the market shows an
intention to reverse into an uptrend and
that indication of a shift again in into
an uptrend is a change of character that
breaks the lower high so it creates a
higher high then a pull back to the
downside that stays above the previous
lows so it created a higher low so
essentially it printed a market
structure of an uptrend and then the
price action should be printing bullish
breaks of structure now from the
downtrend price going down pull back to
the upside breaks the lows and prints a
bearish break of structure pull back to
the upside break of the lows
bearish break of structure and it keeps
going until the breaks the lower high
which creates a higher high and it
maintains above the lower Low by
creating a higher low this is change of
character and if price breaks the higher
high and still maintains above the last
low it basically confirms the bullish
break of structure that has shifted the
market trend from a downtrend into an
uptrend and the bullish breaks of
structure keep printing until the price
breaks the lows while not being able to
break the highs so it essentially
printed a change of character and the
confirmation of the reversal happens
when the price pulls back again to the
upside doesn't manage to break the highs
and instead it breaks the lows so this
creates a bearish break of structure and
the market has essentially reversed
again so this is a presentation how a
market can shift from a downtrend into
an uptrend and into downtrend again now
into the more complex price action in
which after we will analyze on a
Candlestick chart upside pullback break
of the high that marks the following
bullish break of structure now we enter
into the more complex price action the
price pulls back so remember that the
pullback on an uptrend is a downtrend on
the lower time frames so knowing that we
can also apply the breaks and shift
concept on this price action for example
here we have a bearish break of
structure caused by the low time frame
price breaking down the last lows
essentially creating lower
lows then price pulls back to the upside
and stays below the last High meaning
that it created another lower high then
break of the last lows by creating
another lower lows so another bearish
break of structure so what often happens
is when price respects the high time
frame Trend in this case an uptrend the
low time frame Trend aligns with the
high time frame Trend and moves into the
same direction which in this case it's
to the upside this break to the upside
is met by a change of character inside
the pullback this type of change of
character is named an internal change of
character or an internal Market
structure shift so this indicates that
the low time frame Trend could soon
reverse to follow the high time frame
Trend the confirmation of the reversal
is done by Price not being able to break
the past low so by creating a higher low
and breaking the past High by creating a
higher high and this confirms an
internal bullish break of structure in
which price follows through the high
time frame and continues the macro Trend
and from the complex downtrend price
action here we will also apply complex
reversals price going down and pulls
back to the upside the pullback is a low
time frame uptrend with the opposite
Market structure from the higher time
frame price action so the price forms
higher highs and higher lows inside the
lower time
frame with internal bullish breaks of
structure this pattern repeats until the
the price is unable to break the last
higher High inside the low time frame
and it goes down breaking the last
higher low which price forms a lower
high and lower low so it forms the
fundamental price movement of a
downtrend this changes the character by
Shifting the internal Market Trend and
essentially the internal price aligns
with the high time frame moving into the
direction of the main Trend which is a
downtrend and it breaks the high time
frame low so it created a bearish break
of structure on the high time frame and
this price action typically repeats
internally so again pull back to the
upside side internal higher highs and
internal higher lows that forms the
internal bullish breaks of structure up
until the price can't break the last
higher high and it goes break the last
higher low which creates a lower high
and a lower low this has formed an
internal bearish change of character
that aligned the low time frame Trend
with the high time frame Trend
essentially moving the same way which is
to the downside so basically the price
action of the first part of the
structure repeats itself that is because
the price has yet again changed
character into a bearish standpoint so
that means that we have a pullback to
the upside a high that is not able to
break the last High meaning it has set a
new lower high and it breaks the last
lower low setting a new lower low with
its own bearish break of structure to
the downside and once again pull back to
the upside can't break the last High
which sets the price as a new lower high
then breaks the last lower low and sets
a new lower Low by breaking down and
leaving another bearish break of
structure and the same process happens
on the next one we can see here that
price breaks the last major or external
low which creates a new external bearish
break of structure so it confirms the
breakdown of the last external lower low
and it is looking to create a new lower
low in the high time frame so basically
the high time frame and low time frame
were aligned up until this point where
the market was unable to break the last
external low and enters into a low time
frame up Trend by breaking the previous
internal lower low which marks a new
internal higher low and that validates
the new internal bullish change of
character from which price action
confirms the uptrend by continuing the
uptrend price structure so by creating
internal higher highs and internal
higher lows with their own internal
bullish breaks of structure and the
price goes up to break the last external
lower high and by breaking it sets a new
external higher high with its own
external bullish change of character
we have marked with the purple dots
every external level with the blue dots
every internal level the price action
from above so the black lines is the low
time frame price action and the one
below with the orange lines is the high
time frame price action the direction
and price is the same in both time
frames only the action and structure we
see is different and the structure is
very important for Traders to analyze
setups and finally let's jump into the
chart and apply what we have learned
this is the euro dollar on The Daily
time frame the market initially started
from an uptrend if we simplify the price
action this is the upside movement
marking a higher high then the price
pulls back as we have mentioned before
the pullback is a low time frame
downtrend with its own internal bearish
breaks of structure we can't see them
the best here because for that we need
to move into a lower time frame to
observe the low time frame price action
on the pullback for example switching
from the daily chart into the 4-Hour
chart chart but we have the most
important part which is the internal
change of character this structure marks
the end of the pullback and validates
the formation of the high time frame
higher low this shifts the low time
frame structure and aligns the price
with the high time frame by going up
breaking the last High time frame higher
high and creating another high time
frame higher high then we have another
pullback but it breaks the last higher
low which marks a new high time frame
lower low and this is a high time frame
change of character character pay
attention and see how price action
behaves similarly like we have explained
on the line presentations so we got the
first indication of a market reversal by
the uptrend breaking the last low
remember what we have mentioned before
that the reversal confirmation happens
only once the price pulls back to the
upside is unable to break the last highs
and instead it breaks the previous lows
essentially creating the downtrend
fundamentals and those are lower highs
and lower lows it is only now that the
downtrend has been validated and see how
price pulls back to the upside again but
the maximum Highs are lower than the
last maximum highs and since this Market
has entered a downtrend the market could
run to break the lows again up until it
shows a reversal sign and the reversal
sign that we use is a change of
character to the upside now that we have
learned how the markets moves and its
structure it's time to learn the trading
entry models the first one we are going
cover is the supply and demand supply
and demand man zones are price levels or
areas where smart money are most
actively trading with the largest volume
so that helps us identify these levels
and follow the smart money
footsteps if you look at any Financial
Market be it stocks crypto Forex we
should know that the markets move in
certain Cycles they go from balance to
imbalance and the then Market moves from
imbalance towards balance in other words
the market always chases efficiency fair
pricing and a fair chance for both
buyers and sellers to enter a market a
balanced price looks like this it moves
like a Consolidated or ranging Market it
essentially shows that buyers had the
same strength as the sellers therefore
the market creates a choppy price action
the balance must be broken it's how the
nature of the markets is and this break
of balance is called an imbalance an
imbalance in the market is created once
the market is pushed aggressively out of
balance this movement is often made by
smart money and large institutions with
very very large amounts of money
remember what we have said before the
market moves towards balance we can
apply this information because from this
imbalance the market will eventually try
to rebalance itself and the rebalance is
indicated by two zones that we will talk
about these zones are called supply and
demand zones let's start with to explain
what is the supply the supply zone is
met within two types of price action one
type is the reversal Supply Zone this
zone is characterized by price going up
creating a ranging movement sideways and
going all the way back down this whole
price action is also often named as a
rally base drop the second type of
Supply is the continuation Supply Zone
this zone is defined by Price action
that drops significantly to the downside
then started a slow downtrend and breaks
to the downside again this whole price
action is named a drop base
drop now for the demand we we also have
two types of price action within the
demand zones one type is the reversal
the reversal is seen by Price going down
creating a consolidation or ranging
market then the price breaks all the way
upside this movement is named as a drop
base rally then the second type of
demand is the continuation the
continuation is seen by a significant
upside movement then a slow upside
movement and another significant upside
movement this market movement is named a
rally base rally so you should be able
to notice how the market is balanced
then it breaks the balance and becomes
an imbalanced or inefficient market and
the market looks to rebalance itself as
we have said before the balance is when
prices moving Fair towards both
directions so in simpler terms once a
market is ranging and an imbalance
market is when the price does not give
Fair chances to one party either the
buyers or the sellers now that we know
what demand and supply are we need to
know how to identify them and how can
they be used by Traders the supply is a
Zone where the market has been balanced
and it suddenly broke the balance to the
downside so this zone is the supply zone
so knowing this sharp move has
imbalanced the market as we have said
multiple times before the market moves
towards balance and we wait for it to
happen this translates to waiting for
the price to come back up into the
supply Zone this gives Traders a sell
short opportunity but under certain
conditions that we will soon learn them
now for the demand Zone it is
essentially the opposite way around the
market has been balanced then breaks the
balance by Price going to the upside in
a very aggressive way the Zone where
price has moved before the break is the
demand zone now that the market is
imbalanced it wants to move towards
balance that translates into price
moving back down to the demand Zone this
gives Traders a buying opportunity
we will soon see how to filter the moves
in such a way we can identify
highquality zones but for now let's
present how to identify the supply and
demand zones using candlesticks finding
and using these supply and demand zones
is relatively simple and it is done by
following some steps the first step is
to look for a candle or a small series
of candles with large volume that breaks
the balance by pushing the price
aggressively either to the upside or to
the downside in this certain scenario
this move is to the downside
now that we have identified that candle
we move into the Second Step which is to
observe the candle previous to the
candle that broke the balance so to make
sure we understand we are talking about
the last candle before the price has
moved aggressively so that is this
candle now that we also identified the
candle we move into the third step which
is to take the high and low of that
candle so the high and low of the candle
from the second step and draw a Zone to
the right you can can do that by using
lines but the most common it is marked
by a rectangle or box and this rectangle
zone is the supply Zone the supply zone
is used If eventually price comes back
up to rebalance the market the price has
a high probability of rejecting to the
downside from The Zone and this gives
Traders an opportunity to snipe sell
short
positions now for the demand Zone the
first step is to find an aggressive move
towards to the upside a move that breaks
the Market's balance
the second step is to identify the
candle before the aggressive move the
third step is to Mark the high and low
of that candle and we wait for the
market to rebalance by Price eventually
going down and rejecting the zone to the
upside giving Traders a setup for a
buying
opportunity now let's look in the charts
and actually see what we have learned
the market is ranging so we are in a
balance Market this candle is
significantly larger than the previous
ones meaning that this candle had the
largest amounts of volume
this price action overall unfortunately
does not imply usual large movements so
this might not be the best setup and we
will explain later how to find the best
possible setups but until then the
candle before the move is this so we
take the high and low of the candle and
this is the supply Zone what we expect
for this Market is for it to eventually
and slowly come back up to rebalance
point where the most often met scenario
once price hits a supply zone is for it
to reject to the downside and break the
lows so it finally rebalanced the
market and it met our expectations to
reject to the downside and soon after it
also broke the lows essentially
continuing the downtrend
another example this is a clear very
aggressive
uptrend in which the market comes back
down to rebalance then the market prints
these two large upside candles a balance
broken to the upside marks a demand Zone
and the demand zone is taken from the
candle before the large movement so this
red candle we take the high and low from
this candle and this zone is our demand
Zone our expectations is for price to
rebalance Itself by going back down into
the demand Zone gathering enough
liquidity and then rejecting the demand
Zone to the upside essentially breaking
the last major High since we know this
is an uptrend we look for highs to get
broken and let's see what we get from
following the upcoming
price so the price hits the demand Zone
moves around for a bit probably because
it hasn't gathered enough liquidity yet
so we need patience the key point is for
price to not break below the demand Zone
and soon after these large candles
printed on the chart rejecting the
demand Zone to the upside and let's see
if they can manage to break the last
major
high and yes they did so far we have
learned the market structure which
teaches us how and why a market moves a
certain way and supply and demand zones
which are an entry
strategy to understand how highquality
supply and demand zones work we must
understand Market structure the market
structure knowledge can be applied into
the supply and demand and this is what
we are going to talk about now so let's
take a downtrend which creates lower
highs and lower lows in downtrends we
look for Supply zones like this one
right here so applying Market structure
knowledge we see this is a downtrend
with bearish breaks of structure in the
high time frame on the downtrend we
expect a pullback to the upside and as
we have said in the first chapter the
pullback is a low time frame uptrend so
price action creates internal bullish
breaks of structure knowing we have a
supply zone right above we would expect
the pullback to end near the supply zone
so the price rejects down the supply but
pay attention as most Traders would
probably just sell short right at the
touch and that can be a viable option
but the highest quality setup is as it
follows after the price hits the supply
Zone we wait for the market to break the
last low so essentially we wait for
price to create create an internal
bearish change of character we do not
Place orders yet as we have said in the
first chapter the change of character is
the first big indication of the reversal
but the confirmation of the reversal
happens after price pulls again back to
the
upside point where we should be able to
recognize that there is another Supply
Zone internally on the lower time frame
Supply Zone where smart money places
their sell orders and for price to hit
the zone and continue the confirmed
downtrend by breaking structure in the
high time frame essentially making a new
high time frame lower low now for the
demand zones considering a high time
frame uptrend so a market structure that
goes up pulls back to the downside does
not break the last lows and it pushes to
break the last high this bullish break
of structure confirms the validity of a
demand Zone as we have said before the
demand zone is the last move before an
impulsive push to the upside a price
push that breaks the Market's balance
and most importantly it is a valid
demand Zone because the market has
respected the uptrend by making higher
highs in the high time
frame after price has pushed out of
balance the market moves to rebalance
and that is done by pulling back to the
downside so essentially creating a low
timef frame downtrend with internal
bearish breaks of structure the target
of the downtrend is the demand Zone
because the demand zone is a rebalance
of the market so what we look for is
price hitting the demand Zone
having a rejection to the upside and
price breaking the last internal lower
high this move validates the reversal in
the lower time frame which means that
the low time frame is soon looking to
align with the higher time frame and
this validates another demand Zone
inside the lower time frame in which we
look for buying opportunities once price
pulls back hits the demand aligns with
the high time frame and pushes to break
structure of the last high in the high
time frame essentially creating a new
higher high in the high time
frame now let's check into the charts
this is the gbpusd Forex pair on the
2hour time frame we already Market the
zones for you on this chart example we
should be able to quickly and easily
notice an uptrend so let's start the
analysis we see an impulsive upside
movement remember what we have said in
the first minutes of the video an
impulsive upside movement with a large
candle signals a potential upcoming
uptrend that is currently unconfirmed
confirmed the confirmation comes when
price pulls back doesn't break the last
lows and it breaks to the upside that is
what we call a break of structure and
notice we called the E break of
structure it comes from external break
of structure external meaning High time
frame so after price breaking the highs
and setting a high time frame break of
structure in an uptrend we get a
confirmation of a valid demand zone now
we can see that this demand Zone has not
been hit yet but there should be no
problem successful and profitable
trading is heavily based on patience and
self-control if a zone is not hit
instead of forcing the trade and going
out of your plan it would be a better
idea to have patience for the right
setup and respect your plan the market
has another push to the upside pull back
to the downside marking a higher low
then a higher high by breaking the last
high and setting another external
bullish break of structure now in this
case we did not have a good enough
demand Zone to take into consideration
the reason was main L of this candle
taking the previous lows of the demand
Zone making it a risky Zone to validate
so we just waited for price to keep
repeating the uptrend structure by
pulling back to the downside after the
significant bullish movement then a
large candle with increased momentum
breaks all the recent low time frame
lows and highs so essentially it created
a low time frame or internal change of
character we are soon going into these
zones to explain it in more
detail but first let's continue the high
time frame price action analysis
so after creating that Trend shift
inside the low time frame it confirms a
demand Zone which we can see this demand
Zone would give a textbook perfect entry
an immediate bullish reaction right at
the touch then as we have explained in
the Lin's presentation a textbook
perfect takeprofit would be at the last
highs because being in an uptrend we
expect the market constantly have
external bullish breaks of
structure we have explained the high
time frame charting but remember from
the first first minutes this important
part an uptrend has a high time frame up
movement then a pullback now remember
that in an uptrend the pullback is
actually a low time frame downtrend so
we are now zooming into this whole
downside price action we are moving from
the 2-hour time frame into a lower time
frame let's say the 30 minute this one
is completely fine because it's not very
far from the initial High time frame
while being low enough to have a good
understanding price action so notice the
downside movement pull back to the
upside and break of the lows this marks
a bearish internal break of structure
the eye from the break of structure
stands for internal and essentially the
internal bearish breaks of structure
keep
printing the market manages to break a
lower high which marks a higher high and
this movement is a bullish change of
character inside the low time frame the
trend shift validates a demand zone now
if you wonder why this demand zone is
taken from multiple candles well the
demand zone is taken from the higher
time frame it's taken from one candle in
the higher time frame after we have seen
the first candle larger than the
previous ones the play and shift between
time frames is very important the price
is the same in both time frames the time
frame doesn't change the price but the
price action is different between time
frames the price action shows how the
market has moved around a price and the
movement is what helps Traders identify
good setups the change of character
shifts the trend into a low time frame
uptrend and it basically aligns the low
time frame Trend with the high time
frame by creating internal bullish
breaks of structure up until the price
hits the low time frame demand fills the
orders from the smart buyers reacts very
aggressively to the upside breaking both
another internal break of structure and
breaking the external break of structure
this is the complex demand entry
essentially identifying a high time
frame demand Zone and executing in the
low time frame more than likely many
smart Money traders had their buy orders
on the top of the demand Zone with stop
loss below the demand Zone and take
profit right above the last High time
frame external higher high why there
because being in a high time frame
uptrend the expectations of the Market's
movement is to constantly break highs in
the high time frame going back into the
high time frame and zooming into the low
time frame in this zone so into this
pullback and this is how it looks pretty
similar to the last one we know there is
a high time time frame uptrend by the
aggressive upside movement and the
pullback printed afterwards and this is
the pullback which is a low time frame
downtrend inside a high time frame
uptrend it works similarly as the last
Market structure with internal bearish
breaks of structure in the low time
frame essentially creating lower lows
and lower highs this structure repeats
until the low time frame pushes the
price up breaks the last internal lower
high prints the bullish internal change
of character which validates the demand
Zone before the push in this case we
have taken the demand Zone only from
this time frame and from one candle to
make it more simple but we can even go
to a higher or even lower time frame to
find and even more quality demand Zone
but that is a bit Overkill in my opinion
the very complex and advanced concepts
are most of the times not worth it
because positives always comes with new
negatives and the negatives of setting a
very difficult and complex strategy
usually comes with missing a lot of
trading opportunities so anyway after
validating the demand Zone the price
slowly Trends down hits the demand Zone
gathers liquidity and pushes the market
up this push can also create a new
demand Zone which you can take from the
lower or the higher time frame depending
on your preference the best idea is to
not go too far away from the initial
time frame where you have made the main
analysis on then the same action as the
last one low time frame aligns with high
time frame and breaks the internal
structure and also the external
structure in the high time frame so it
essentially continues the high time
frame Trend the next concept also used
for trade entries is the fair value Gap
often shortened and spelled as
fvg the fair value Gap is a concept that
explains that large sharp movements
makes the market inefficient the theory
is similar to the supply and demand
zones mostly because both breaks the
Market's price and make it unfair for
one side of participants buyers or
sellers and in the case of the fair
value Gap it is the level where the
market becomes inefficient and it is
used for trade entry strategies because
once price comes back to fill the
inefficiency you will often see a
reaction on these levels it is important
to know that the fair value Gap is met
more rarely than the supply and demand
let's look at a downtrend line chart
before using the Candlestick chart
because it makes it easier to understand
as we know in an uptrend the price
creates higher high and higher lows
on uptrends we look for demand zones for
the pullback to hit the demand zones and
potentially give Traders opportunities
for buying positions but the pullback
doesn't always just hit the demand Zone
considering the price keeps holding the
uptrend this is where the fair value Gap
comes in where the price is pulled back
filled the fair value Gap and continued
the uptrend the traders that have waited
for the demand Zone to hit have lost the
opportunity while the ones that took
from the fair value Gap app successfully
capitalized on this
setup we will soon explain in what
situations you can analyze to determine
if you would look for the fair value Gap
or look for the demand Zone but for now
let's also explain it from the
downtrend on a downtrend the price goes
down pulls back to the
upside situation where there might be
formed Supply zones to take the price
down and basically continue the
downtrend but the pullback might also
end low lower than anticipated and that
might be because of a formed fair value
Gap that filled the inefficiency before
hitting the supply Zone and the filling
of the inefficiency on a downtrend
validates the continuation of the
initial macro Trend which is a downtrend
now we want to identify the fair value
Gap using candles and then we jump into
the charts first we will present it for
the uptrend we want to look at a
sequence of three candles where one of
them has pushed very aggressively with a
higher momentum than the previous one on
the previous candle should have its high
Wick lower than the entire body of the
large candle and the third candle which
is the next candle from the larger one
should have the lower Wick higher than
the whole body of the large candle
notice how if we Mark with a line the
high Wick of the first candle with the
low Wick of the third candle we get a
Zone this is the fair value Gap in an
uptrend scenario notice the inefficiency
created and this area can be used as an
entry strategy once price comes back
down to fill the zone and now for the
downtrend scenario the rules are similar
we want to look for a sequence of
candles usually three or four there must
be a large candle with a larger momentum
than the previous ones the candle
previous to the larger one should have
its lower Wick higher than the whole
large candle and the candle next to the
large one must have its higher Wick
lower than the whole body of the large
candle and we take a line or any
instrument to Mark the low Wick from the
first candle and the highwick from the
third candle and this is the bearish
fair value Gap that can give Traders an
opportunity for sell short orders once
price fills the
inefficiency this is the US dollar
against the Japanese yen in the 2-hour
time frame from the left of the chart
the market has been in a shortlived
uptrend with only one bullish break of
structure before price breaking the
swing lows and essentially changing
character into a bearish structure the
change of character validates the
presence of the follow bearish fair
value Gap this is the first candle the
second candle is the large candle and
the one next to the large one is the
third candle there is a noticeable small
price inefficiency and we Mark the zone
as we have learned keep in mind we look
for the formations of fair value gaps as
soon as we can identify them but we take
them into consideration only if the
trend or Market structure validates the
fair value Gap so we should be able to
identify the fair value Gap soon after
it printed on the chart but in this
Market structure the validation comes
only after the we have a trend change
because if we are right here the bearish
Gap has appeared but the market is still
bullish for The Gap to be the highest
quality we wait for the structure to
change character into the same Trend
that the fair value Gap was printed so
into a bearish trend in this case and we
simply wait for the price to fill the
inefficiency then take a sell short
position with the stop loss above the
last swing high and take profit below
the last swing low these targets make
sense because because on downtrends we
do not expect the price to make higher
highs instead we expect the market to
make lower highs this was the
explanation for the positioning of the
stop loss and for the takeprofit on a
downtrend we do not expect the market to
make higher lows instead we expect the
market to make lower lows so a break of
the last lows the break of the lows is
itself a bearish break of structure what
happens after a push to the downside in
a downtrend a pull back to the upside
and then continuation of the bearish
trend by breaking the lows then the
market gains bullish momentum and we
notice the formation of a bullish fair
value Gap this is the first candle the
second candle is the large one and the
third candle is the next one from the
larger one and this zone is the bullish
fair value Gap but the problem here is
that the market has not validates this
fair value Gap because the market was
still in a downtrend when the Gap has
appeared the bullish change of character
so the trend change from a downtrend
into an uptrend has happened after the
Gap has already filled so this is a
lower quality fair value Gap that in
this situation it has worked we signaled
it as a counter Trend fair value Gap
trading against the trend is really
difficult we did not take this trade
even if the setup has worked there are
countless more opportunities taken the
future be responsible and avoid taking
unwanted risks all right but after we
get another large bullish fair value Gap
this one is the first candle the large
candle is very visible and the third
candle what we expect is for the market
to come back down move around this Zone
and reverse to the upside essentially
continuing the recently created uptrend
by breaking higher
highs now I have some tips for you since
this zone is very large what we can do
is to wait for the price to come back
down switch to a lower time frame look
for a bullish change of character
and a formation of a demand zone or a
fair value Gap inside the lower time
frame look for buy order opportunities
and follow the price action to take
profits on the break of the higher
highs if you noticed we usually use the
higher time frames more
often this one is the NASDAQ futures in
the 5minute time frames this one is a
lower time frame chart and the reason we
do not use lower time frames very often
is because of false signals and low
quality structures for example look at
this these are all fair value gaps the
first one from the lowest point didn't
got filled the second one from above got
broken down the third one also didn't
got filled it's only the fourth fair
value Gap that got respected this is the
first candle the second candle is the
large one the third one is the candle
next to the large one and by marking the
zones we see price filled the
inefficiency with a wick and reverse to
the upside so this was a valid fair
value Gap and even the next one from the
above so the fifth fair value Gap did
not fill from five fair value gaps we
got only one that has worked one that
has failed and three that did not fill
and price just continued pushing to the
upside I'm not saying that low time
frames inefficiencies do not work they
can work but they are much harder to
analyze and need complex knowledge to
filter them out and increase your
chances of success as much as possible
but why complicate it so much when you
can just have more
patience switch to a higher time frame
and do the analysis there to give a
perspective on using low time frame fair
value gaps we will trade a couple of
examples during a back test so the
market is in a downtrend the Wix fill
all inefficiencies so basically there is
no significant bearish fair value Gap
present to trade but there is a bullish
fair value Gap now that is this very
risky to take because we are taking buys
into a downtrend basically we are
trading against the trend of course the
trend can reverse but trying to predict
the reversal is very difficult but since
this is a back test we will take a buy
if the inefficiency gets filled so we
are placing a buy order on the top of
the
Gap the stop loss below the lows the
take profit above the highs and this is
about a one to two risk to reward not
the worst but not the best so let's see
what the price does
the position was
opened and the trade was a one let's see
the continuation of the price action and
by the way we got a bullish change of
character since the market has broken
the last high and we got the pull back
and the break of the highs so
essentially we are in an uptrend now
there is another fair value
Gap buy orders at the top stop loss
below the
lows and sadly we do not have really
good takeprofit Targets this being a
lower risk to reward trade I will expand
the position to at least a 1 to two and
leave this position for
longer now there's another fair value
Gap
stop loss below the lows take profit to
at least one to two risk to reward let's
see if we can get a 1 to three we can
also place the stop loss below the fair
value Gap that could give us a higher
risk to reward but it can come with more
stop losses being
hit keep in mind the pass position is
still running so we are in two buys at
the same time
and both positions hit take
profit the difference between time
frames is quality and hit rate in low
time frames just as we have traded
recently the hit rate is high the
quality is low and the risk to reward is
low in high time frames the hit rate is
low the quality is high and the risk to
reward is high so in the high time frame
we would need only one or two high
quality setups to gain the same total
risk to reward ratio as we would in a
low time frame the last one was a low
time frame now it's time to also look
into a setup on a high time frame to
give as example back testing so this
Market is clearly bearish looks like it
initially was in an uptrend and failed
to keep the bullish momentum making
sellers gaining control and taking over
this Market before looking for setups we
need to analyze the market right here
for example we got an ascending trend
line with liquidity resting below that
shortly after got taken by breaking the
trend line to the downside the downtrend
is easily identified by the bearish
breaks of structure we got one right
here then another one another break of
structure and one more so far the market
is pushed to the downside in a very
aggressive manner right until the last
visible price action where it looks like
bearish momentum is decreasing the lower
Wicks also signal a liquidation of
orders the price action so far looks
like smart money is preparing something
we are not taking any positions yet as
there is no significant confirmation or
any kind of relevant enough detail for a
setup so let's play the price action and
wait until we can spot an
opportunity finally the time for some
upside movement this is a very
aggressive upside Movement we should
have fair value gaps but first make sure
to Mark the bullish change of character
so we do not forget that the market
might reversed into an uptrend this
change of character also validates the
presence of a fair value Gap the fair
value Gap is not this because we can
clearly see the lower Wick of the large
candle almost covers the body of the
previous candle making the price
efficient enough to not be taken into
consideration the actual fair value Gap
is found here I will the zone to make
sure we do not get lost in between
lines and we place a buy order on the
top of the fair value gap for the stop
loss we have multiple options like
placing the stop loss below the lows or
placing it below the Gap since this is a
higher time frame and the setup quality
should be higher I will place the stop
loss below the zone and we will also
have a higher risk to reward ratio
looking for at least a 1 to three risk
to
reward good the position got filled and
notice the immediate reaction to the
upside we are looking for the price to
break the highs so essentially we want
the market to create a bullish break of
structure since the market has changed
character from a bearish standpoint into
a bullish one
the trade has hit the takeprofit but
let's just look if it actually managed
to break the
highs and yes it did the next concept we
are going to cover is the breaker block
a breaker block is an order block that
failed to hold and flips into a new
order block for the opposite trend for
the sake of Simplicity the order blocks
are the supply and demand zones and this
is how it works in an uptrend we are
going to use a bearish breaker block
let's explain why we have the uptrend
price making higher highs and higher
lows the pullback having their demand
zones zones that can be valid or not if
they are valid we know what happens as
we did Cover in the first couple minutes
of the video the price breaks the highs
and continues the uptrend but if it
fails to hold so essentially it creates
a new lower low and this is a bearish
change of character now we have multiple
options to look for setups
so far we learned that on this situation
we look for a supply Zone near the top
and previously we learned that if there
is no significant Supply Zone we can
look for inefficiencies that create fair
value gaps and both strategies can be
used however we can also use the breaker
blocks the demand Zone got broken turns
into a supply the new Supply is named a
bearish breaker block from which we look
for price to reject to the downside once
the market hits the zone and in a
downtrend Trend the market structure
creates lower lows and lower highs with
Supply Zones near the
pullbacks the supply zones hold up until
a point where selling momentum decreases
and buyers take control over the market
situation in which the supply Zone can
get broken to the upside so basically it
creates a bullish change of character as
we have learned we can look for the
demand zones to take the market higher
we can look for bullish fair value gaps
but we can also look for the bullish
breaker block
the broken supply Zone flips into a new
demand Zone which is called a bullish
breaker block and we look for price to
hit it and reject to the upside
essentially continuing the trend that
recently has reversed if you wonder why
so many entry strategies well you don't
need all of them all you need is
understanding the fundamentals so
understanding the market structure and
liquidity and choose only one entry
strategy and master it before moving
into another
one some Traders even combine the
strategies but that is much more
difficult so by using only one entry
strategy you will miss the trades that
don't apply to your strategy but that is
completely fine as much as you learn
knowledge is pointless without a strong
discipline and
patience let's check some examples on
the chart starting from the left this
Market structure clearly shows a
short-term downtrend structure seen by
Price creating lower lows with bearish
breaks of structure and lower highs this
type of that moves sign significantly in
one side and then shortly after it
recovers all the way back this type of
movement is often seen when liquidity is
pulled in large amounts in small price
areas most likely a liquidation of buy
orders so taking the stop losses of the
buyers to load up and prepare the orders
for smart money to push in the exact
opposite side soon after the buyers
observed a loss of sellers momentum and
a gain of buying momentum seen by this
more significant upside movement than
the other pullbacks from the left of the
chart so many buyers probably have been
thinking by this large up candle that
the market should soon reverse to the
upside so they were opening buy orders
just for price to take their stop losses
and liquidated their
positions the very aggressive downside
movement coupled with the fact that the
market was in a downtrend at this level
validates the following Supply Zone
after liquidating the buyers the market
drove up to the supply and instead of
holding the supply and rejecting to the
downside the supply has failed and the
market broke above it since we cannot
really predict what's coming let's
assume that we as traders that use Smart
money Concepts have sold short this
Supply zone so we have gotten stopped
out of the trade with a loss but with
the proper risk management just like we
have shown in the previous examples
where we look for at least one to two or
1 to three risk to reward ratio this
means that a win covers multiple losses
so after getting stopped out the trend
reverses because the market broke the
last significant High essentially
changing character into a bullish
standpoint now we can look for demand
zones or fair value gaps but on this
chapter of the video we are talking
about breaker blocks remember from the
first minutes of explaining the details
about the breaker block the failed
Supply turns into a bullish breaker
block so essentially it becomes like a
demand Zone and we can clearly see the
price reaction with many Wicks that have
been bought back to the upside and sell
momentum decreasing basically making
buyers taking over the trend now the
market is trying to print a bullish
break of structure to the upside and as
we can see later it did and the second
example for the breaker block the market
was initially on an uptrend
characterized by the bullish breaks of
structures and price making higher highs
and higher lows each swing low becomes
closer to the previous swing low showing
exhaustion of buyers and selling
pressure yet the market continues its
trajectory by making higher
highs the change of character happened
before but the reversal was not
confirmed we can easily see how the
swing lows broke the last one so the
change of character extends for longer
but the reversal confirms only when the
market also fails to create new highs
point where if we choose to learn and
use the breaker blocks we look for the
last demand Zone to fail by basically
breaking down so as it did and the
failed demand turns into a new Supply
Zone as we call it a bearish breaker
block from which price hits the Zone
giving Traders an opportunity to analyze
if they want to place sell short orders
the markets fill those orders and
rejects the price to the
downside and we came to the end in this
video we have learned how to read and
analyze the market and as well as the
three most powerful trading strategies
understanding the topics discussed
should build you a strong knowledge base
of smart money Concepts there are a
couple more things that we will talk
about in a future video but those are
small complex details that are not
really needed in most cases the most
effective way is understanding the
market structure and its liquidity in a
way to make you feel confident in
analyzing the market and choose one
entry strategy out of the three that we
have talked about combine it with the
market structure and master it smart
money Concepts can get pretty
complicated in this video we shortened
it and explained it in a simple way with
proper examples for each of the details
learned in the video in a way that even
beginner Traders can understand this
work was possible because you guys
support us so if you want to keep up the
production of our videos you can by
encouraging us by leaving a like And
subscribe to our Channel and leave
feedback and questions in the comments
all right thank you for watching